I am going to suggest something very simple, it's just to be aware of
the inhale and the exhale.
Then we will learn to follow the inhale.
This will lead us to a consciousness, that is to say, within us, we have an energy.
We have several levels of energy.
We have a level of energy that we call mindfulness.
This means that in life, you must learn to digest.
Also learn to discern. Most of the time, we are not discerning,
we are in judgment. So we will return to a quality of our mind with
another
energy that we call concentration. Finally, I must be aware of the inhale
and the exhale in all its movement. Once
I have this awareness of the inhale
and the exhale, it's as if I could unite.
My mind and my body.
I arrive at a state where I am in the present moment.
Most of the time, we are not in the present.
Most of the time, we are in the past.
A lot of symptoms, in the end, many illnesses come from the past.
We are like stuck in the labyrinth of the past.
I suggest that for a few moments, we be fully aware, here
and now.
Once you have this awareness,
If this represents, for example, a breath movement, I
have a breath movement,
I am fully aware of my inhale and
my exhale.
If you do this, you will increase the energy of concentration. This
will bring you to a level where you
unite the mind and body,
which means that you start to become
aware of your body.
When you become aware of your body,
you begin
to feel your body, so you have sensations.
Here, I unite
through these two levels,
I will unite
consciousness
with the body. When I have this awareness,
I must
move to the fourth level. There are
16 levels. I will teach you about
8. It is to learn to release the body. You release the body when you
are aware of
the exhale. You will stimulate the vagus nerve and
when you stimulate the vagus nerve, you stimulate your
parasympathetic system. When you stimulate your parasympathetic system, you
stimulate your
recovery and repair system. This means you will have an effect
on your prefrontal system.
You will activate your cerebral cortexes
which will intersect
and help the recovery of the body.
Awareness at the exhale
leads to healing.
It is a very ancient teaching.
I am aware of my inhale
and my exhale.
In the body,
we also have movements of inhale and exhale.
We will learn
little by little, in the body, to be fully aware
of the inhale and the exhale.
Because this brings you to mindfulness, which is an energy where,
when I need to be
fully aware, I could divide mindfulness into
an object and a subject.
I am fully aware of something.
This means that I am either objective
or subjective, or the subject of something.
This brings my mindfulness together with the energy of
concentration
which will gradually lead you, with practice, to what
we call the third energy,
what we call deep vision.
Because you will start to free yourself from your sensations.
That is to say, you will be able to use them.
Because most of the time, you react to sensations.
And you lose your freedom.
An emotion arises in my mind.
It happens so fast that I don’t see.
But I have a sensation, in fact.
When you feel anger, you have a sensation in your body.
And you learn to observe that sensation.
So we will do this exercise to start, we will be fully aware of
the inhale
and the exhale, we will follow the inhale
and the exhale, we will unify, that is to say, we
will take
awareness of our body and then we will learn to relax it.
These are the first four steps to gradually
enter into this awareness of self-presence, in
the present moment.
The present is a gift. That's why we call it a present.
And I like the idea of giving ourselves this gift.
So let’s give ourselves a little presence to ourselves.
This is where we say, if we don’t start with ourselves, we are just, because then we discover love.
And you can close or not your eyes
it might be easier at first
when you start
and you will simply
very simply
be fully aware
when you inhale
you are fully aware
And in fact, when you make this little movement, you are fully aware when you inhale,
you have a kind of freedom, for 3-4 seconds you are free, you
are free from your thoughts
of the past, you are free from your future.
You are just for a few seconds, you
are free, and then if you want to continue.
This freedom, you do the same thing at the exhale. You
are fully aware of the inhale and
the exhale. And then you learn gradually, to
increase the energy of concentration,
you learn to follow the movement. I am
fully aware
of my inhale.
I follow it in its entirety.
If you do this, you will see that you will increase the energy of concentration.
Ultimately, it is such a simple act,
but so simple and so profound.
And then you...
You contact your body.
You contact the physical, etheric body.
You contact your feet, the sensation of
contacting the ground.
And then the body as a whole.
And you breathe consciously.
I connect with my body, I
become aware, I am, follow the
totality of
your breathing act, you will relax at the exhale, now
you connect
with the exhale, and at the exhale you
let go.
You relax the body
to prepare for listening
to return to the moment
in the present moment
very quickly you see that there are thoughts
that arise
because that’s the nature of the mind
it’s thought
and in Zen, we say
you watch
it’s a bit
inspiration and you observe the train of thoughts and
you don’t go along with all the
thoughts but there will be one that is stronger and will capture you
and you
will go along with it until you realize that
you are not
in the present moment anymore. There you develop what we call a
tool of
what we call vigilance.
If you have vigilance,
you return to the simple act,
to this simplicity of the inhale and the exhale.
For us, as osteopaths,
the inhale and the exhale are important.
Because ultimately, this movement in the body,
even in the primary respiratory movement,
you have an inhale and an exhale.
a flexion, an extension
an opening
and a closing
and it is important to have freedom
in this movement, in the body
it is the minor movements
that will govern these movements
that will govern these major movements
so we will go more and more
into this finesse
of the inhale, of the exhale
to find the still point
if you do not understand the vacuum
it is difficult to make a true still point because in the still point of
emptiness there
can be a re-emergence of the vital process. When someone
comes to see you, we will try to
search for the origin and cause of this illness, for example, patients come
with a
concern, it is necessary to recognize this concern in people; from the non-recognition
arise all the compensatory states. You will try to see, look, there is a symptom.
And many people, in fact, many therapists, they are just there. They remain
in this object because they have not recognized a primitive concern.
At a certain point,
here, there is a line, you see, and you have to guide people
towards a point of balance. That is,
a point of balance, a balance towards a
healing process, it is the life process that
is
to restore trust in life, that
means restoring joy, it is very important to understand
this. Sometimes there are people who come to me and I just talk, I
talk
until a moment when I become aware of this,
and I guide them towards that.
Because if they leave with joy, you are in
the therapeutic phase.
You open the movement.
Many people get stuck there.
Yes, I’m searching here, I’m searching here, I’m here.
And they tell you, yes, I know very well.
People leave ultimately with a symptom.
They remain with a concern.
They should not leave with their words.
They must leave with the right word.
So when you bring that movement, you bring a potentiality into your body.
You bring a force.
It is easier when you are joyful, when you have this happiness within you, to
heal.